Guide to the Engravings
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
[Engravings].
1787-1810
OSBORN FD49
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.14
(1 volume)
Collection of satirical engravings by Robert Dighton, James Gillray, James Sayers, and C. Williams. The prints are primarily devoted to political satire; and the subjects include John Bull; taxes; French sympathies in Great Britain; George III's reaction to the Catholic Bill; the Broad-Bottomites in the Cabinet; and the public orator William Crowe. Titles include "A noble Lord, on an approaching peace, too busy to attend to the expenditure of a million of the public money"; "Doublures of characters, or striking resemblances in physiognomy"; "An ex minister training a terrier at Bowood"; and "All the talents upset or the highmettled Hanoverian grown restive." Several of the prints have been hand-colored.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
For provenance information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The following finding aid is a complete inventory of the contents of Osborn fd49. This list was reformatted from previously existing cataloging.
Engravings, British; John Bull (Symbolic character) -- Caricatures and cartoons; Political satire, English -- 19th century; Taxation -- Great Britain; France -- Foreign relations -- Great Britain; Great Britain -- Foreign relations -- France; Great Britain -- Politics and government -- 1760-1820; Engravings (prints); George, King of Great Britain, III, 1738-1820 -- Caricatures and cartoons; Crowe, William, 1745-1829; Dighton, Robert, 1752-1814; Gillray, James, 1756-1815; Sayers, James, 1748-1823; Williams, C.
- Osborn fd49
  - DIGHTON, ROBERT, 1752?-1814
    - "A Celebrated Publick Orator", [1808 Jan] (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      colored etching of William Crowe
      (1745-1829)
      31 x 23 cm.
      Published 1808 Jan, by Dighton,
      Charing Cross
      BM 11062
      fd.49
  - GILLRAY, JAMES, 1757-1815
    - "Doublures of Characters; --or-- striking Resemblances in Physiognomy.", [1798 Nov 1] (Box 1)
      satirical print, engraving
      36 x 26 cm.
      Published 1798 Nov 1, by J. Wright,
      Piccadilly
      BM 9261
  - GILLRAY, JAMES, 1757-1815
    - "John Bull and the Sinking Fund--a p/r/etty scheme for Reducing the Taxes and paying off the National Debt!", [1807 Feb 23] (Box 1)
      satirical print, colored engraving
      40 x 28 cm.
      Published 1807 Feb 23, by H.
      Humphrey, St. James's Street
      BM 10704
  - GILLRAY, JAMES, 1757-1815
    - "A noble Lord, on an approaching Peace, too busy to attend to the Expenditure of a Million of the Public Money", [1787 Mar 12] (Box 1)
      satirical print, aquatint
      37 x 27 cm.
      Published 1787 Mar 12, Southwark, by
      R. Phillips
      BM 7150
  - GILLRAY, JAMES, 1757-1815
    - "a Petty-Professor of Modern History, brought to Light.", [1810 Mar 20] (Box 1)
      Published 1810 Mar 20, by H.
      Humphrey, St. James's Street, London
      BM 11590
  - SAYERS, JAMES, 1749-1823
    - "An Ex Minister training a Terrier at Bowood", [1794 Mar] (Box 1)
      satirical print, etching
      1798 Mar [n.d.]
      28 x 22 cm.
      BM 9179
  - SAYERS, JAMES, 1748-1823
    - "A Peep over the Garden Wall in Berkeley Square", [1794 Mar 17] (Box 1)
      31 x 25 cm.
      Published 1794 Mar 17, by H.
      Humphrey
      BM 8440
  - WILLIAMS, C.
    - "All The Talents Upset or the Highnettled Hanoverian Grown Restive.", [n.d.] (Box 1)
      37 x 26 cm.
      BM 10716
  - WILLIAMS, C.
    - "Fishing for Flats or a Drag from the Stock Exchange.", [1806 Jul 25] (Box 1)
      34 x 24 cm.
      Published 1806 Jul 25, by S.W. Fores
      of Piccadilly
      BM 10587
  - WILLIAMS, C.
    - "God Save the King - by a New Set of Performers - being their first Appearance these twenty Years", [1805] (Box 1)
      Published 1805 [sic] by Walker,
      7 Cornhill
      BM 10541
  - WILLIAMS, C.
    - "Making-Decent; --i.e.--Broad- bottomites getting into the Grand Costume", [1806 Feb] (Box 1)
      satirical print, engraving, uncolored
      35 x 25 cm.
      Published 1806 Feb, by S.W. Fores,
      BM 10531A
  - WILLIAMS, C.
    - "Reposing on a Bed of Roses.", [1806 Apr] (Box 1)
      Published 1806 Apr, by Walker,
      BM 10559
  - WILLIAMS, C.
    - "That! for all the Talents.", [n.d.] (Box 1)
      BM 10711